# **Yunming Xiao**

2233 Tech Drive Seely Mudd, Room 3-416 Evanston, IL 60208 yunming.xiao@u.northwestern.edu □+1 (773)-273-0957 yunmingxiao.github.io

#### RESEARCH INTEREST

I am broadly interested in computer networks. My current research focuses on two primary directions: (i) enhancing the security and privacy measures of various Internet services, and (ii) advancing the reliability of data center networks, aiming to minimize downtime.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science

Sep 2019 - Present

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL Advisor: *Prof. Aleksandar Kuzmanovic* 

# **B.Eng.**, Computer Science

Sep 2015 - Jun 2019

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, Beijing, China

GPA: 3.7/4.0 (87/100), Graduated with Honors

#### RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCE

## Northwestern University, Evanston, IL

Sep 2019 - Present

Research Assistant, Advisor: Prof. Aleksandar Kuzmanovic

- PDNS: A Fully Privacy Preserving DNS
  - Proposed and developed PDNS, a novel DNS system that provides full privacy perseverance to users by leveraging the single-server Private Information Retrieval (PIR) techniques
- Snatch: Streaming Analytics at the Network Edge
  - Proposed and developed Snatch, a system that enhances user privacy and accelerates online streaming analytics by breaking the current arrangement and leveraging semantic cookies
- Monetizing Spare Bandwidth: the Case of Distributed VPNs
  - Performed the first systematic measurement study of the decentralized VPNs ecosystem
- Decoding the Kodi Ecosystem
  - Perform the first systematic measurement study of Kodi's decentralized ecosystem
  - My developed system SafeKodi has received multiple media coverage and is used by over 30K users

## Teaching Assistant:

- COMP SCI 397/497: Selected Topics in Computer Networks Spring 2021, 2022, 2023
- COMP SCI 340: Intro to Computer Networking Winter 2022
- COMP SCI 110: Intro to Computer Programming Fall 2020

# **Hewlett Packard Labs, Milpitas, CA**May - Aug 2022 (Full time) & Jan 2023 - *Present* (Part-time)

Research Intern, Networking and Distributed Systems Lab, Host: Dr. Puneet Sharma

- Proposed a SmartNIC-aided control framework for machine learning workloads orchestration
- → Winner of the Best-in-Class Technical Competition Award (2nd Place)

#### Google, New York City, NY

Sep - Dec 2022

Software Engineering Intern, Technical Systems & Infrastructure (TI)

• Built the first prototype for migrating the network transport for Keystore service from gRPC to Pony Express

## Nokia Bell Labs, Murray Hill, NJ (Remote)

Jun - Aug 2021

Networking Bell Labs Summer Intern, Host: Dr. Matteo Varvello, Dr. T.V. Lakshman

• Built FIAT, a third-party system that frictionlessly authorizes IoT traffic by learning recurring traffic and validating human actions behind less predictable traffic

## Bytedance, Beijing, China

Infrastructure R&D Intern

• Worked on Cronjob and FaaS systems of Bytedance Cloud

Tsinghua University, Beijing, China

Mar 2018 - Mar 2019

Research Assistant, Host: Prof. Wenfei Wu

King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, Jeddah, KSA

Jul - Oct 2018

Visiting Student, Host: Prof. Marco Canini

Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications, Beijing, China

Jul 2017 - Feb 2018

Research Assistant, Host: Prof. Bin Wu, Prof. Jingyu Wang

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

(\* Equal Contribution)

## **Conference Publications**

- [6] C Miao\*, Y Xiao\*, M Canini, R Dai, S Zheng, J Wang, J Bu, A Kuzmanovic, Y Wang: TENSOR: Lightweight BGP Non-Stop Routing.

  To appear in ACM SIGCOMM'23.
- [5] **Yunming Xiao**, Matteo Varvello:

FIAT: Frictionless Authentication of IoT Traffic.

In Proceedings of ACM CoNEXT'22.

■ [4] Yunming Xiao, Sarit Markovich, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

Blockchain Mining: Optimal Resource Allocation.

In Proceedings of ACM Advances in Financial Technologies (AFT'22).

■ [3] Yunming Xiao, Matteo Varvello, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

Monetizing Spare Bandwidth: the Case of Distributed VPNs.

In Proceedings of the ACM on Measurement and Analysis of Computing Systems (SIGMETRICS'22).

■ [2] Marc Anthony Warrior, Yunming Xiao, Matteo Varvello, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

De-Kodi: Understanding the Kodi Ecosystem.

In Proceedings of The Web Conference 2020 (WWW'20).

■ [1] **Yunming Xiao**, Haifeng Sun, Zirui Zhuang, Jingyu Wang, Qi Qi:

Common Knowledge Based Transfer Learning for Traffic Classification.

IEEE 43rd Conference on Local Computer Networks (LCN'18), short paper.

#### **Journal Publications**

■ [4] Yunming Xiao, Matteo Varvello, Marc Anthony Warrior, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

Decoding the Kodi Ecosystem.

ACM Transactions on the Web (TWEB). 2023.

■ [3] Aritra Dutta, El Houcine Bergou, Yunming Xiao, Marco Canini, Peter Richtárik:

Direct Nonlinear Acceleration.

EURO Journal on Computational Optimization. 2022.

[2] P Wang, Y Zhao, MS Obaidat, Z Wei, H Qi, C Lin, Y Xiao, Q Zhang:

Blockchain-Enhanced Federated Learning Market with Social Internet of Things.

IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications (JSAC). 2022.

■ [1] **Yunming Xiao**, Bin Wu:

Close spatial arrangement of mutants favors and disfavors fixation.

PLoS Computational Biology, 15(9), e1007212. 2019.

Mar - Jul 2019

#### Refereed Demos/Posters

[2] **Yunming Xiao**, Matteo Varvello:

FIAT: Frictionless Authentication of IoT Traffic.

In Proceedings of ACM CoNEXT'21.

[1] **Yunming Xiao**, Matteo Varvello, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

A First Look Into Distributed VPNs.

The 21st ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC'21).

## **Un-refereed & Working Papers**

[3] Y Liu\*, Y Xiao\*, C Miao, X Li, Z He, H Liu, W Dang, A Kuzmanovic, J Wang:

Omitted for double-blind review.

On Submission.

■ [2] Yunming Xiao, Chenkai Weng, Ruijie Yu, Peizhi Liu, Matteo Varvello, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

Omitted for double-blind review.

On Submission.

■[1] **Yunming Xiao**, Yibo Zhao, Sen Lin, Aleksandar Kuzmanovic:

Omitted for double-blind review.

On Submission.

#### **PATENTS**

[2] Yunming Xiao, Diman Zad Tootaghaj, Aditya Dhakal, Puneet Sharma:

Conspirator: A SmartNIC Aided Control Plane for Distributed Machine Learning Workloads.

On Submission.

[1] Diman Zad Tootaghaj, **Yunming Xiao**, Aditya Dhakal, Puneet Sharma:

A bin packing-based GPU job scheduling for tenant isolation.

On Submission.

### **GRANTS**

Helped with the proposal for NSF grant CNS-2226107: "Enabling Streaming Analytics at the Network Edge" (\$400K, PI: Aleksandar Kuzmanovic).

## **INVITED & CONFERENCE TALKS**

Conext 2022, "FIAT: Frictionless Authentication of IoT Traffic", Rome, Italy (Remote), December 2022. Nokia Bell Labs, "FIAT: Frictionless Authentication of IoT Traffic", Murray Hill, NJ, November 2022. SIGMETRICS 2022, "Monetizing Spare Bandwidth: The Case of Distributed VPNs", Mumbai, India (Remote), June 2022.

### **SERVICES**

Program Committee member, ACM SIGCOMM 2022 Artifact Evaluation

Reviewer, ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review (CCR)

Reviewer, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications (JSAC)

Reviewer, Journal of Systems Architecture (JSA)